Have you ever wondered
if there’s a natural way
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
You can’t buy an
epigenetic clock,
but you can use one to measure
the age of your tissues and cells
and to predict health outcomes
and life expectancy.
In our first story,
we look at how epigenetics
have surpassed telomere length
as the best age predictor.
Epigenetics—the differential
expression of genes—
both establishes the character
and function of a cell
and maintains that identity
over time
through round after round
of cell division.
So, a heart cell
stays a heart cell
and divides
to make more heart cells,
instead of skin cells
or kidney cells,
even though all our main cells
have the same
entire complement of DNA
to potentially be anything.
This is accomplished
by methylation,
chemical markers that silence
inappropriate genes
in a particular cell.
The fidelity
of that maintenance
of methylation is good-
97 percent to 99.9 percent
every division-but not perfect.
Over time, those tiny errors
may add up
and may help explain why
the methylation patterns
of identical twins
drift apart as they age.
The epigenetic markers
of young identical twins
are essentially
indistinguishable
but then diverge over time.
Identical twins have
the same DNA, the same genes,
but the difference
in gene expression
among older
identical twin pairs
were found to be
about four times greater
than those observed
in young pairs.
This may result in them each
getting different diseases.
An age-related disease
like Alzheimer's
only has an identical twin
concordance rate
of about 50 percent,
meaning if one twin gets it,
there's only
about a coin flip chance
that the other will too,
despite identical DNA.
Or, even if they do
both get it,
the disease may manifest
decades apart.
Any epigenetic differences
that may contribute
to differential disease rates
may arise from having
different diets and lifestyles
or may be a result
of random epigenetic drift.
However, there are
certain DNA sites
on our chromosomes
that predictably methylate
or demethylate as we age.
So predictable, in fact,
it's like clockwork.
One of the earliest attempts
to study aging
and the epigenome
(which is only
like a dozen years ago)
found that the DNA
from a 103-year-old
appeared to be
less methylated overall
than the DNA
of a newborn infant,
suggesting, perhaps,
that aging involves
the general loss
of epigenetic markings.
We now know
it's more complicated than that.
Of the methylation sites
that reliably change as we age,
about 60 percent go
from methylated to unmethylated,
and the other 40 percent become
more methylated over time.
Some so reliably change
with age
that they've been considered
a "molecular crystal ball
for human aging."
In a remarkable triumph
of Big Data,
out of the millions
of methylation sites
in our DNA,
a tiny subset
so dependably shift over time
that you can predict
someone's age
within a few years
just by strategically measuring
the methylation pattern
in a few hundred
or even just a few dozen sites
in someone's
three-billion-letter genome.
Over just the last few years,
these "epigenetic clocks"
have become established
as robust measures
of chronological age,
surpassing telomere length
as the best age predictor.
Who cares, though?
I mean, why invent some costly
Rube Goldberg approach
to divining someone's age
when you can simply ask them?
Well, you can imagine
forensic applications,
the determination
of an unidentified victim's age
with a blood sample,
but that's just scratching
the surface.
The kicker is
that epigenetic clocks
don't just track
your chronological age
but appear to measure
your true biological age.
In other words,
your epigenetic age
can better predict
your remaining life expectancy
than your calendar age.
It's like science fiction.
Feed a drop of blood
into some futuristic machine
that scans the placement
of chemical markers
on a strand of DNA,
and it spits out your true age,
reflecting a lifetime
of lifestyle choices.
If the machine calculated
that you have
the DNA methylation pattern
of a 60-year-old, but you've
only had 50 birthdays,
that would be an example of
"epigenetic age acceleration,"
when your epigenetic clock age
is older
than your actual
chronological age.
That would be an indication
that you're aging too fast.
As a 50-year-old,
you'd think you have another,
mm, 30 years on this Earth,
but because
the epigenetic clock shows
that you're aging
at such an accelerated pace,
it's more like you only have
another 20 years left.
Every five years
of epigenetic age acceleration
is associated
with an 8 to 15 percent
increased risk of mortality.
In addition to predicting
time-to-death,
epigenetic clocks
also appear to foretell
healthspan indicators,
such as cognitive decline,
frailty, arthritis,
and the progression of diseases
like Alzheimer's
and Parkinson's.
As you can imagine,
the insurance agency*
has jumped on this,
and your premiums
may soon be determined
by your epigenetic age.
But it's not some
Gypsy fortune teller curse
set in stone.
You can change the rate
at which you age
and may soon be able
to use epigenetic clocks
to track your progress,
potentially presenting
a radically faster
and cheaper way to test
anti-aging interventions.
In our next story,
we look at how a baby with
a heavy surrogate mother
and a thin biological mom may harbor
a greater risk of becoming obese
than a baby with a slim surrogate
mom and a heavy biological one.
Identical twins don't just share
DNA; they also shared a uterus.
Might that also help account for some
of their metabolic similarities?
Fetal overnutrition, evidenced by
an abnormally large birth weight,
seems to be a strong predictor of
obesity in childhood and later in life.
Could it be you are what your mom ate?
A dramatic illustration from the
animal world is the cross breeding
of Shetland ponies with massive
draft horses. I mean, either way,
the offspring are half pony, half
horse, but in the pony uterus
they come out much smaller—
thank heavens for the poor pony.
This is presumably the same reason
why the mule—donkey dad and mare—
is larger than the hinny—
stallion and donkey mom.
The way you test this in people
is to study the size of babies
from surrogate mothers
after in vitro fertilization.
Who do you think most determines
the birth weight of a test-tube baby:
the donor mom who
provided all the DNA
or the surrogate mom who provided
the intrauterine environment?
When it was put to the test,
the womb won.
Incredibly, a baby born to
an obese surrogate mother
with a skinny biological mom may
harbor a greater risk of becoming obese
than a baby from a big biological
mom born to a slim surrogate.
The researchers conclude the
environment provided by the mother
is more important than her
genetic contribution to birth weight.
The most compelling data comes from
comparing obesity rates in siblings
born to the exact same mother before
and after her bariatric surgery.
Compared to their brothers and
sisters born before the surgery,
those born when mom weighed about
100 pounds less had lower rates
of inflammation, metabolic
derangements, and most critically,
three times less risk
of developing severe obesity,
afflicting 35% of those born
before the weight loss,
compared to 11% born after.
The researchers conclude these
data emphasize how critical it is
to prevent obesity and treat
it effectively to prevent
further transmission
to future generations.
But wait. Mom had the same
DNA before and after surgery.
She passed the
same genes down.
How could her weight during
pregnancy affect the weight destiny
of her children any differently?
Darwin himself admitted
that the greatest error he
committed had been not allowing
sufficient weight to the direct action
of the environment, like food,
independently of natural selection.
We finally figured out the mechanism
by which this can happen: epigenetics.
Epigenetics—literally meaning above
genetics—layers an extra level
of information on top of the DNA
sequence that can be both affected
by our surrounds and potentially
passed on to our children.
This is thought to explain the
developmental programming
that can occur in the womb
depending on the weight
of the mother, or even
your grandmother.
Since all the eggs in your infant
daughters' ovaries are already
preformed before birth,
a mother's weight status during
pregnancy could potentially affect
the obesity risk of her grandchildren
too. Either way, you can imagine
how this could result in an
intergenerational vicious cycle
where obesity begets obesity.
Is there anything
we can do about it?
Well, breastfed infants may be
at lower risk for later obesity,
though the benefits may be
confined to exclusive breastfeeding,
as the effect may be
due to growth factors
triggered by exposure to the
excess protein in baby formula.
The breastfeeding data
is controversial though,
with charges leveled
of a white hat bias.
That's the concern that public health
researchers might disproportionally
shelve research results that doesn't
fit into some goal for the greater good—
in this case preferably
publishing breastfeeding studies
showing more positive results—
but of course that's coming from
someone who works for
an infant formula company.
Breast is best regardless;
its role in the childhood obesity
epidemic just remains
arguably uncertain.
Prevention may be the key.
Given the epigenetic influence
of maternal weight during
pregnancy, a symposium
of experts on pediatric nutrition
concluded that planning
of pregnancy, including prior
optimization of maternal weight
and metabolic condition,
offers a safe means to initiate
the prevention rather than
treatment of pediatric obesity.
Easier said than done, but overweight
moms-to-be may take comfort
in the fact that after the weight
loss in the surgery study
even the moms who gave birth to kids
with three times lower risk were still,
on average, obese themselves,
suggesting weight loss
before pregnancy is not
an all-or-nothing proposition.
Finally today,
how the anti-inflammatory and antioxidant
properties of plant-based diets
may explain why they can
effectively reverse cellular aging
by elongating telomeres.
Identifying simple strategies
to prevent or delay age-related
diseases is a major
public health concern.
But how could you measure
the effects of such strategies?
Well, telomere length is a reliable
hallmark of biological aging
and the risk of developing
age-related chronic diseases.
What is a telomere,
and why does it matter
how long they are?
Telomere comes from the Greek for
"end" "part" of our chromosomes.
Telomeres cap the ends
of our chromosomes
like shoelace tips to essentially
keep our DNA from fraying.
Telomere length is important since
there's a minimum length required,
but every time our cells divide,
a bit of the telomere is lost
and once they get too short,
the cell can die.
That's why telomeres are sometimes
called the molecular clock of cells.
Every year they get shorter and
shorter, kind of like life's fuse,
but in some people that fuse
burns faster than in others.
Accelerated telomere shortening
has been identified as a key biomarker
for accelerated aging, disease risk,
and diminished longevity.
But there's some good news.
Telomere shortening can be
counteracted by an enzyme
in our cells called telomerase.
Telomerase can replenish the lost
bits and elongate our telomeres.
So how can we boost this enzyme
to, in effect, reverse cellular aging?
Exercise may help.
Those with high levels
of physical activity
have longer telomeres,
whereas obese individuals and smokers
tend to have shorter telomeres,
along with those getting
inadequate sleep.
But what about nutrition?
Globally, we might expect that any
antioxidant or anti-inflammatory diet
could be protective for telomeres.
So we're talking like
a whole food plant-based diet
with a reduced intake of meat and,
in fact, swapping out animal protein
in general in favor
of plant-based proteins.
Given that plant-based foods
have well-known antioxidant
and anti-inflammatory effects,
there are fair grounds to believe
that the consumption
of plant-based foods
can help to counteract
telomere attrition,
but you don't know if it actually
would, until you put it to the test.
Dr. Dean Ornish, along
with the Nobel laureate
who co-discovered
the telomerase enzyme,
studied the effects of
comprehensive lifestyle changes
on telomerase activity
and telomere length
using the same plant-based
diet and lifestyle program
shown to reverse the progression
of heart disease and
early-stage prostate cancer, and
maybe even early-stage Alzheimer's.
And telomere length shortened
in the control group,
and they aged five years
as expected,
but didn't just not shorten
as much or hold steady,
but actually lengthened in
the plant-based lifestyle group.
Whereas in a similar study
across a similar time frame,
there was no difference in
telomere length when just giving
people the more typical low-fat dairy,
skinless chicken breast,
generic-type
healthier dietary advice.
Antioxidant-rich plant foods
help maintain telomere length.
In contrast, total and saturated fat
intake and consumption
of refined flour grains,
meat and meat products,
and soda relate
to shorter telomeres.
People eating more
anti-inflammatory diets
tend to have longer telomeres,
and the greater the anti-inflammatory
potential of the diet over time,
the greater potential
to significantly slow down
the rate of telomere shortening.
Those with the most
pro-inflammatory diets
had almost twice the risk of
accelerated telomere shortening.
The most pro-inflammatory
food component is saturated fat,
found in meat, dairy, eggs and junk,
along with other pro-inflammatory
food components like
cholesterol and trans fat.
Omega-3's tend to be
anti-inflammatory,
but when put to the test,
fish oil supplements
failed to have any
significant telomere effects.
The most anti-inflammatory
food component is fiber.
And indeed, if you look at dietary
fiber intake and telomere length
in a representative sampling
of thousands of US adults,
even though nobody
was eating enough,
the more fiber people consumed,
the longer their telomeres
tended to be.
Since there appeared
to be a straight-line increase,
they could do the math,
and it appeared that just a 10-gram
increase in fiber per 1000 calories
would equate to four fewer years
of biologic aging,
whereas, for example,
the consumption of soda
appeared to increase cell aging
by almost two years
per daily serving.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.